Register of the Vooruzhennye Sily na IUgie Rossii. Nachal'nik snabzheniia Records, 1916-1926
Hoover Institution Archives
Vooruzhennye Sily na IUgie Rossii. Nachal'nik snabzheniia Records,
1916-1926
30009
Vooruzhennye Sily na IUge Rossii. Nachal'nik snabzheniia
6 manuscript boxes 2.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, receipts, and accounts, relating to the payment of Russian soldiers in Bulgaria and Yugoslavia, financial subsidies to refugees, administration of refugee camp facilities, and the composition and distribution of units of the First Army Corps and the Don Corps
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1930.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Refugees; Soviet Union; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Refugees
Historical Note
These records, together with those of the Justice Department of the Russian Army (Sudnoe Otdielenie Russkoi Armii), were previously accessioned at the Hoover Institution as the F. F. Abramoff collection. Both groups of records at one point were in the possession of General Abramoff, who commanded the Don Army Corps in Bulgaria, but he was not the originator of the records themselves. The office of the Chief of Supply was relocated in Bulgaria after the evacuation of General Wrangel's Russian Army from the Crimean Peninsula in 1920, and was responsible for the distribution of funds to the First Army Corps and the Don Army Corps, both of which were billeted in Bulgaria after 1922. General Abramoff probably assumed possession of the files of the Chief of Supply after many of the Russian Army organizations and offices disintegrated in 1926-1927 because of the acute shortage of funds.
The duties of Lieutenant-General Peter P. Stavitskii, who held the office of Chief of Supply from 1922 to 1926, centered upon the disbursement of funds to needy soldiers and their families, particularly invalids, war widows and orphans, and upon the control of expenditures for barracks, staff and office expenses, military schools and lyceums, Red Cross hospitals, and various military organizations, such as the Medical Department. Most of the material concerns army organizations in Bulgaria (specifically, the First Army Corps and the Don Army Corps) during the period 1922-1926. However, the Chief of Supply was also responsible for the distribution of funds to army organizations in the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, including General Headquarters in Belgrade.
Series Description
- Numerical Office File, 1919-1926. (Box Box No. 1-5.)
  Correspondence, telegrams, lists, tables, charts, maps, accounts, advance accounts, receipts, minutes, balance-sheets, memoranda, certificates, information bulletins, orders, reports, arranged in consecutively numbered folders.
- Subject File, 1916-1922. (Box Box No. 6.)
  Correspondence, reports, protocols, information sheets, tables, lists, receipts, accounts, and service lists, arranged alphabetically by subject.
Container list
- Numerical Office File, 1919-1926.
  - File No. 1. Correspondence, telegrams, lists, reports, and maps relating to the relocation of soldiers of the First Army Corps and the Don Corps in refugee camps in Bulgaria. Correspondence of the office of the Commander of the Don Corps (General Abramoff) and the office of the Commander of the First Army Corps (General Kutepov) with the Chief of Supply (General Stavitskii); correspondence of the Chief of Supply with the Directorate of Labor Conscription (Bulgaria). 1921-1922. (Box 1.)
  - File No. 2. Correspondence, telegrams, lists, advance accounts, orders, reports, charts, and receipts relating to the assignation of funds for construction, repair and maintenance of dormitories and staff offices for the First Army Corps and the Don Corps. Includes letters signed by Generals Kutepov and Abramov. 1921-1922.
  - File No. 3. Correspondence, telegrams, lists, contracts, reports, and charts relating to the construction and maintenance of living quarters for the First Army Corps and the Don Corps, for war invalids, and for students of military schools; to the purchase of living quarters from the Bulgarian Government; and to the relocation of units evicted from their quarters by the Bulgarian Government. Correspondence with the offices of Generals Kutepov and Abramov, and with the Directorate of Labor Conscription; maps and charts showing the distribution of units of the First Army Corps and Don Corps in Bulgaria. 1922.
  - File No. 4. Correspondence, accounts, reports, orders, charts, and lists concerning the allocation of funds for the General P. N. Wrangel Lyceum (a school for children of soldiers of the First Army Corps). Includes correspondence with the Director of the Lyceum (General Savitskii); and one letter from General Wrangel to General Stavitskii, 1922.
  - File No. 5. Correspondence, accounts, tables, charts, lists, and reports concerning the allocation of funds for financial assistance to invalids and needy families, support of military schools, and maintenance of army contingents in Bulgaria (staff and office expenses) and the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. Includes correspondence with the General Headquarters Finance Director. 1923.
  - File No. 6. Correspondence, reports, telegrams, accounts, and lists concerning the allocation of funds for medical supplies and equipment and treatment for invalids. Correspondence with the Medical Department and the office of the Representative of the Russian Red Cross in Bulgaria. Includes one letter from Baroness Olga M. Wrangel (Director of the Committee for Aid to Russian Soldiers and their Families in the Balkans) to General Stavitskii. 1922-1923.
  - File No. 7. Correspondence, telegrams, lists, tables, accounts, and reports relating to the allocation of funds for aid to invalids and soldiers' families, and medical treatment to same. Correspondence with the Russian Red Cross and the Committee for Aid to Russian Emigres in Bulgaria; accounts and minutes from meetings of these organizations. Includes one letter signed by General E. K. Miller. 1924. (Box 2.)
  - File No. 8. Correspondence, telegrams, contracts, minutes, lists, tables, reports, orders, and accounts relating to the allocation of funds for allowances to invalids of the First Army Corps and the Don Corps undergoing treatment in the Russian Red Cross hospitals in Bulgaria. Correspondence with the Russian Red Cross and the Committee for Aid to Russian Emigres in Bulgaria. 1923.
  - File No. 9. Correspondence, telegrams, orders, information bulletins, lists, and charts relating to the allocation of funds for invalids, soldiers' families, and military schools; to the composition of army contingents in Bulgaria; to the "embassy fund" for needy invalids and soldiers' families; to cost-cutting and staff-reduction measures; to the living conditions of Russian soldiers in Bulgaria; and to various financial matters. Correspondence with Generals Abramov, Ronzhin, Kuossonsky, and Miller. 1923-1924.
  - File No. 10. Correspondence, reports, lists, telegrams, charts relating to the allocation of funds for payment of subsidies to invalids and soldiers' families and to the "sisters of charity."1924.
  - File No. 11. Correspondence, telegrams, receipts, reports, minutes, lists, and accounts relating to the allocation of funds for the construction of schools and hospitals for Russian Army contingents in Bulgaria, for aid to invalids and families, etc. Correspondence with the Director of the Finance Section of General Headquarters (Baron A. E. Tizengausen); minutes from meetings of the Finance Council to the Russian Diplomatic Representative in Bulgaria (A. M. Petriaev). 1923.
  - File No. 12. Correspondence, telegrams, accounts, and receipts relating to the allocation of funds for the maintenance of army contingents in Bulgaria, subsidies to invalids and soldiers' families, staff and office expenses, etc. Correspondence with the office of the Director of the Finance Section of General Headquarters (Baron A. E. Tizengausen). 1924.
  - File No. 13. Minutes and extracts from minutes of the Budget and Control Commission at General Headquarters. 1923-1924. (Box 3.)
  - File No. 14. Correspondence, reports, lists, orders, instructions, accounts, and tables outlining the conditions for and levels of financial assistance to soldiers' families and invalids; and relating to the activities of Control Commissions in investigating irregularities in administration of funds. Reports and letters signed by General E. K. Miller; reports of Control Commissions assigned by General Wrangel to certify expenditures of the Kornilov Military Lyceum; the Drozdovskii Rifle Regiment; and the Drozdovskii Artillery Division. 1922-1923.
  - File No. 15. Correspondence, accounts, lists, tables, and reports relating to the activities of Control Commissions investigating the misuse of funds allocated to invalids and soldiers' families. Reports concerning expenditures by the Committee for Aid to Russian Emigres and Russian contingents in Bulgaria; correspondence with the Representative of the Control Commission in Bulgaria (General I. D. Nestorovich). 1923-1925.
  - File No. 16. Correspondence, tables, lists, accounts, reports and orders relating to expenditures by military schools, army units, the Medical Department, the Russian Red Cross in Bulgaria, etc. 1923.
  - File No. 17. Correspondence, telegrams, lists, tables, reports, and accounts relating to expenditures for subsidies to invalids, staff and office expenses, the maintenance of army contingents, schools, hospitals, churches, etc. 1924.
  - File No. 18. Correspondence, lists, tables, accounts, and reports relating to expenditures for subsidies to invalids and soldiers' families, staff and office expenses, maintenance of army contingents, schools, hospitals, etc., and also to curtailment of these expenditures. 1925.
  - File No. 19. Correspondence, lists, tables, accounts, balance-sheets, and memoranda relating to expenditures for subsidies to invalids and soldiers' families, staff and office expenses, maintenance of army contingents, schools, hospitals, etc. 1922-1926.
  - File No. 20. Correspondence, accounts, receipts, certificates, and lists, comprising: 1) advance accounts of the Military and Naval Justice Department of the Russian Army, containing lists of expenditures for office equipment, 1919-1920 (15 account books); 2) advance accounts of the Court of Honor in Bulgaria, 1922 (5 account books); 3) advance accounts of the Director of the Automobile Department of the War Ministry of the Crimean Government, 1919; 4) materials related to the purchase of books and newspapers for military schools and libraries in Bulgaria, 1922. (Box 4.)
  - File No. 21. Correspondence, reports, tables, lists, accounts, and orders relating to: 1) expenditures for staff and equipment for military schools, the Medical Department, the 1st Army Corps, and the Don Corps; 2) the replacement of General P. N. Shatilov by General E. K. Miller as Chief-of-Staff of the Russian Army; 3) requests for arms, ammunition and other military equipment; 4) the export of flour by commercial dealers in Bulgaria to the Society of Holders of the St. George Cross in Constantinople. Includes copies of an exchange in correspondence between General Wrangel and M. N. Giers concerning the critical financial situation in the Russian Army. 1921-1922.
  - File No. 22. Correspondence, reports, accounts, telegrams, lists and tables relating to the allocation of funds for subsidies to invalids and soldiers' families, various military organizations and offices (the Court of Honor, the Medical Department, the Department of Supply, the Control offices, etc.), soldiers' pay, and military schools in Bulgaria and the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes; lists and accounts relating to expenditures by General Headquarters. Includes letters signed by General P. N. Shatilov. 1921-1922.
  - File No. 23. Correspondence, lists, accounts, and reports relating to the allocation of funds for payment of soldiers in the 1st Army Corps and the Don Corps, staff, office, and equipment expenses, military schools, hospitals, etc. 1922.
  - File No. 24. Correspondence, reports, advance accounts, information bulletins, telegrams, and certificates relating to 1) requests for financial support from soldiers, and conditions for the receipt of same; 2) proceedings of the Court of Honor in Bulgaria, particularly with regard to possible abuses in the distribution of funds; 3) requests for background information on certain individuals. Includes letters signed by Generals E. K. Miller, P. A. Koussonsky, and I. A. Ronzhin. 1923. (Box 5.)
  - File No. 25. Correspondence, telegrams, tables, reports, and lists concerning the sale of automobiles formerly used as staff cars by the Russian Army, and repairs to same. 1924.
  - File No. 26. Correspondence, accounts, minutes, reports, orders, lists, charts, and tables relating to the expenditure of funds for subsidies to medical institutions, Russian Officers' Unions, the Lemnos and Gallipoli groups, the Russian military government in Bulgaria, and various emigre newspapers. Minutes of the Conference of Senior Commanders in Bulgaria; charts detailing expenditures for foodstuffs and medical supplies for patients in the military hospitals; accounts of the 5th Division of R.O.V.S. and the Lemnos and Gallipoli groups. Includes letters signed by Generals Kuossonsky and Abramov. 1924-1925.
  - File No. 27. Orders, instructions, lists, and tables comprising directives issued by General Wrangel, General Poliakov, Colonel Elizarov, and the Lemnos Group in Bulgaria, mostly related to some aspect of supply. 1923.
- Subject File, 1916-1922.
  - Bredoff, General. Service lists of the General Bredoff Detachment, 1916-1920. (Box 6.)
  - Emigres, Russian - Bulgaria. Correspondence, information sheets, lists, tables, protocols, receipts, and accounts comprising correspondence with the War Ministry of the Bulgarian Government relative to the Russian Army Contingents in Bulgaria (in Bulgarian). 1921-1922.
  - Koloboff, Colonel M. V. Correspondence, reports, and service list relating to the Special Russian Mission in the Slavic Countries (Commission for the Collection and Preservation of Military-Historical Documents), an anti-Bolshevik propaganda organ headed by Colonel M. V. Koloboff. 1920-1921.